Guide to the David Gitin Papers, 1968-1993.
Department of Special Collections
Gitin, David. Papers,
1968-1993.
M0691
Gitin David
.25 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
David Gitin edited Bricoleur, corresponded with Oppen from 1968-1977. He published Oppen, sought his editorial eye when writing poetiy himself, welcomed his support when he wentjob-hunting. Oppen had sustained correspondence in this periodwith Michael Heller, Armand Schwerner, Levertov & Michael Cuddihy, but probably not many others. Serendipity sold for Gitin letters a decade ago, but that lot did not include Oppen, as I remember it. Below is a detailed list ofthe Oppen file, and as a courtesy, a register of everything else Gitin brought in last week, for though it is tempting to sell these others singly in various directions, to maximize profits, it is not courteous to Stanford to do so: I include all the non-Oppen for a lump sum additional, as indicated. Gitin did not cooperate with Rachel Blau who did a SELECTED LETTERS for Sulphur, publishing mostly letters to her. Our letters are unpublished. Sometimes Oppen addresses Joyce Gitin. Oppen & Gitin were often in the same city together (SF), & therefore met, did not correspond. In this period Oppen's SEASCAPE is published & COLLECTED POEMS is in progress. Rough drafts ofPRIMTTIVE appear in the correspondence, a bit.
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1994.
Provenance
Purchased, 1994.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Primarily incoming letters (42) from George Oppen, 1968-1977, including Oppen manuscripts and photographs. Rough drafts of PRIMITIVE appear occasionally in the correspondence. There is a 39-page photocopy of a corrected typescript by Mary Oppen, a journal kept during the couple's trip to Israel. There are also four folders of letters (and some manuscripts) from other writers, 1971-1993.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Amirkhanian, Charles.; Baraka, Imamu Amiri, 1934-; Bly, Robert.; Bromige, DAvid.; Cage, John.; Corman, Cid.; Creeley, Robert, 1930-; Dawson, Fielding.; Di Prima, Diane.; Dorn, Edward.; Eigner, Larry, 1927-; Enslin, Theodore.; Evans, George, 1948-; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-; Gray, Darrell, 1945-; Kyger, Joanne.; Marshall, Jack, 1936-; McClure, Michael.; Meltzer, David.; Oppen, George.; Oppen, Mary.; Owen, Maureen, 1943-; Palmer, Michael, 1942-; Rakosi, Carl, 1903-; Robinson, Kit, 1949-; Silliman, Ronald, 1946-; Sward, Robert, 1933-; Tarn, Nathaniel.; Vega, Jeanne Pomy.; Waldman, Anne.; Wieners, John, 1934-
Collection Contents
- Part I. Correspondence with George Oppen
  - 1. Responding to Bricoleur. Mentions Weinberger, Aug 9, 1968, TLS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 2. On Jeffers.Jan 6, 1969, TLS, 1p (Folder 1)
  - 3. Very descriptive of place - Maine spots.July 14, 1969, TLS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 4. Responding to Gitin's poems with very close exam.Dec 15, 1969, TLS, 2pp (Folder 1)
  - 4 lines, response to Gitin poem, enclosed, Feb 10, 1970, TNS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 6. Gitin is very promising; Oppen is an old man; one poem of Gitin's is irritating.Feb 15, 1970, TLS, 1p (Folder 1)
  - 7. Tiny ink sketch. n.d., 5 lines. (Folder 1)
  - 8. gift for Gitin new home: From "Some Fan Francisco Poems". n.d., Poem typed 1p, signed "George". (Folder 1)
  - 9. Short ANS, he heard Gitin on radio-"very fine indeed".May 23, 1970 (Folder 1)
  - 10. 1 line ANS. "stay well y corragio George".June 2, 1970 (Folder 1)
  - 11. "Dear Novice... Sept 17, 1970, 12 line TLS. (Folder 1)
  - 12. 2 line ANS.Nov 23, 1970 (Folder 1)
  - 13. Copy of Oppen's recommendation of Gitin. "during last three years I have talked on numerous occasions...I have been Feb 28 1971, Carbon TS 7 lines (Folder 1)
  - 14. Tinkering with a poetic line.April 28 1971, TNS, 4 lines (Folder 1)
  - 15.. On Maine, the beats, Kenner.July 30, 1971, TLS, 1p (Folder 1)
  - 16. Continuation ofcontent from previous letterJuly 31, 1971, TLS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 17. About Gitin & poetry itself.Dec 13, 1971, TLS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 18. "Good Luck!"/"George."Jan 30, 1972, TLS (Folder 1)
  - 19. Went to Stanford to hear Gunn & Levine. Praises Rod Taylor & his FLORIDA EAST COAST CHAMPION. My beloved former wrapper Chuchk Miller did the illus for that book!April 13, 1972, TLS, 1p, with a poem in the text (Folder 1)
  - 20. TL to Maria, Yes on Gitin, no on Vangelisti, Oct 13, 1972, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 21. On language; holing up; Sumac book due.Nov 9, 1972, TLS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - 22. Close responses to poems.n.d., TLS, 1p. (Folder 1)
  - APC23. Jan 2, 1973 (Folder 2)
  - 24. On Gitin's response to his book. On Bunting.Feb 13, 1973, TLS, 1p (Folder 2)
  - 25. 6 line ANS.March 25, 1973 (Folder 2)
  - 26. "Teaching, lecturing, showing off, whatever"April 1973, TLS, l/2p (Folder 2)
  - 27. Readings in offing, good that Ginsberg & Cage responded.April 5, 1973, TLS, 1p (Folder 2)
  - 1p. 28. Responds to Gitin's work. "I am limited, obsessed by my own purposes."Oct 31, 1973, TLS (Folder 2)
  - 29. Sending proofs to press. Theorizes about poetiy, succinctly.Nov 11, 1973, TL, 1p (Folder 2)
  - 30. TLS, plus Gitin's poem, ANNOTATED BY OPPEN.Jan 5, 1974, 2pp (Folder 2)
  - 31. To Maria Gitin. ANSMarch 22, 1974, 1p. (Folder 2)
  - 32. On meaning in poetry.April 16, 1974, TLS, 1/2 p. (Folder 2)
  - 33. On Gitin's bibliog of Oppen, article I guess.Oct 7, 1974 (Folder 2)
  - 34. note on letter from Botoomfish Mag ed to Oppen forwarded to Gitin.Jan 22, 1976 (Folder 2)
  - 35. ANS, he would like the EPICTETUS also. To Maria Gitin.May 1976 (Folder 2)
  - 36. Long TLS, 1p to Christopher Middleton recommending Gitin, with cover ALS to GitinOct 15, 1976, 1p. (Folder 2)
  - 37. TLS from Middleton to Oppen, with note, Oppen to Gitin., 1p. (Folder 2)
  - ALS, full page (unusual), with typed poem enclosed "for safe-keeping"June 6, 1977 (Folder 2)
  - 38. "THAT WHICH IS STRANGE" - Best letter so far., 2pp. (Folder 2)
  - 39. ALS, full, very unusual for Oppen to use this mode.Aug 3, 1977, 3pp. (Folder 2)
  - 40. ALS, On Oppen bibliog.Aug 1977, 1p. (Folder 2)
  - 41. On Gitin divorce, remarkable little Un.d., l/2p. (Folder 2)
  - 42. TLS Nov 25, 1977, l/2p. (Folder 2)
  - Nice photo of Duncan, Oppen, Enslin, & Economou at Grand Rapids, 8 x 10. (Folder 7)
  - Oppen. EPIGRAM., Typed poem, 1p (Folder 7)
  - Oppen. UNDER THE HOT SUN IN THE SOIL. MSS POEM, signed, 1p. (Folder 7)
  - Oppen. ORIGINAL VERSION of Oppen's DISCRETE SERIES TS, Xerox (Folder 8)
  - Vincent (Steve) THE BALLAD OF ARTIE BREMER. SF: Momo1974 (Folder 9)
  - Oppen (George) -., 3 snapshots (Folder 10)
  - Oppen (Mary) Oblong mounted photo (Folder 10)
    vintage print, on porch with family as young woman, RARE. Plus vintage mounted photo ofMary Oppen at a young girl.
- Part II. Other Correspondence
  - 1. Charles Amirkhanian. APC 1984 (Folder 3)
  - Robert Bly, ALS1973, 1p. (Folder 3)
  - 3. David Bromige. APC (Folder 3)
  - 4. John Cage. ANS 1975 (Folder 3)
  - 5. Cid Corman. APC,; ALS, 1989.; TLS, 1989.1984 (Folder 3)
  - 6. Fielding Dawson. TPCS,. About Gitin's THE CALL.1984 (Folder 3)
  - 7. Robert Creeley. APC, 1984; APC, 1973. Poem APC,.1977 (Folder 3)
  - 8. LeRoi Jones (Baraka) APCS; T biog resume, annotated, 8x10 photo, 3pp (Folder 3)
  - 9. Diane Di Prima. APC; Brdsde poem, "Peter Hartman's Sequence" 1991, signed,. (Folder 3)
  - 10. Edward Dorn. ANS, 1991 (Folder 3)
  - 11. Larry Eigner. Tpoem, on env flap; TLS, 4pp, including Xerox (Folder 4)
  - 12. Theodore Enslin, TNS. 1990 (Folder 5)
  - 13. George Evans, APC 1991. (Folder 5)
  - 14. Allen Ginsberg. APC 1977. (Folder 5)
  - 15. Darrell Gray. US,.1977 (Folder 5)
    (poet, suicide; or dead of drink)
  - 16. Joanne Kyger. APC. (Folder 5)
  - 17. Jack Marshall. ALS,.1984 (Folder 5)
  - 18. Michael McClure. 1975, FLEA 100, French-fold,, 1/150 with TLS on leaf Als, 1967; ms (Folder 5)
  - 19. David Meltzer, APC.1984 (Folder 5)
  - 20. Maureen Owen. APC.1979 (Folder 5)
  - 21. Michael Palmer. APC.1993 (Folder 5)
  - 22. Carl Rakosi (Caliman Rawley)1984, TNS (Folder 6)
  - 23. Kit Robinson, ANS,. ALS,; APC, 1986, 1p. (Folder 6)
  - 24. Ronald Silliman. APC; ANS, 1989 (Folder 6)
  - 25. Robert Sward. TNS; TPC,. US, 1990, response to Gitin's book 1990 (Folder 6)
  - 26. Nathaniel Tam. APC,.1990 (Folder 6)
  - 27. Jeanne Pomy Vega. 1978, 1p, Good TLS. (Folder 6)
  - 28. ROMANCE. Brdsde, by Ann Waldman1985, folded as mailed, inscribed (Folder 6)
  - 29. John Wieners. 1973, 2pp.Good ALS (Folder 6)